Guide to the Walter H. Breen papers, 1950-circa 1992.
Breen, Walter H., papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Walter H. Breen papers, 1950-circa 1992
7755
Walter H. Breen
0.3 cubic feet.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, holograph notes and printed material from Walter H. Breen. The archive includes Breen's address book, approximately 90 pages, with extensive notations (referencing Arthur Clarke, Isaac Asimov, among others); approximately 47 typed manuscript pages with extensive hand-written notations on issues relating to homosexuality; approximately 60 typed pages, with extensive holograph notes, relating to the "Breen Developmental Inventory Questionnaire" and notes on the related "Project OJ"; a thirty-three page holograph manuscript by Breen entitled "Numbers are Fun!"; approximately seventy typed pages of poems and short works by Breen, many with holograph corrections; and an 18 page typed manuscript of a play entitled "Erokles", along with a 1958 letter from Burkhardt of Der Kreis/Le Cercle.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Walter H. Breen, 1928-1993, also known as E.Z. Eglinton, was the author of the 1964 book "Greek Love," as well as numerous articles on homosexuality, sexology and numismatics, and the 1953 book "Proof Coins Struck by the United States Mint, 1817-1901." He was married to science fiction writer Marion Zimmer Bradley in 1964. They had two children and separated in 1979. In 1979, his concordance of Bradley's science fiction Darkover series was published, "The Darkover concordance: a reader's guide." He was arrested on child molestation charges in 1990, and in 1991 he was charged with eight felony counts of child molestation. He was sentenced to ten years in prison and died in prison in Chino, California on April 22, 1993.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, holograph notes and printed material from Walter H. Breen. The archive includes Breen's address book, approximately 90 pages, with extensive notations (referencing Arthur Clarke, Isaac Asimov, among others); approximately 47 typed manuscript pages with extensive hand-written notations on issues relating to homosexuality; approximately 60 typed pages, with extensive holograph notes, relating to the "Breen Developmental Inventory Questionnaire" and notes on the related "Project OJ"; a thirty-three page holograph manuscript by Breen entitled "Numbers are Fun!"; approximately seventy typed pages of poems and short works by Breen, many with holograph corrections; and an 18 page typed manuscript of a play entitled "Erokles", along with a 1958 letter from Burkhardt of Der Kreis/Le Cercle.
Also, approximately 50 holograph and typed letters to and from Breen from a number of correspondents, including Avant Guarde publisher Ralph Ginzburg, the Coltsfoot Press, and One Incorporated, beginning in the 1950s. A number of letters relate to Breen's early incarceration for sexual contact with minors. Many relate to personal matters, as well as articles and pending publications. Also, approximately 40 pages of notes made while in prison, “Notes from Hell," and assorted printed matter relating to homosexuality, including "The Eighth Annual Report of the George Henry Foundation." "The Altar of Venus," privately printed in 1959 and with no given author is also included.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Breen, Walter H.
Subjects:
Gay liberation movement.; Gay men--United States--Fiction.; Gay men's writings, American.; Numismatics.; Pedophilia.; Youth--Sexual behavior.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Collecting program: Human Sexuality Collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Resume and 1990 biographical sketch (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Address book, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Silhouette of Mr. W.H." (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Breen Developmental Inventory (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Project OJ (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Numbers are Fun!" (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings (poems and short works), circa 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Erokles, circa 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Reverend Love letter and George W. Henry Foundation report on Breen, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence and notes, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Non coin correspondence, circa 1960-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Yael Dragwyla correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Notes from Hell", circa 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Assorted clippings, postcards, leaflets and Mattachine bylaws, circa 1954-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Copy of sections of "The Sex Atlas" (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "If You Are Arrested..." (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Henry Foundation report, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "Alter of Venus", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)